A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22 FA294
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
1969-1984
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
FA294
6.27 Cubic Feet 18 boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in two subseries:
Subseries 1: Administrative Files
Subseries 2: Grant Files
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: administrative and grant files.
War relief; United States; Mental health; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Medicine, Rural; Medical research; Medical education; Legal research; Legal issues; Law; Hygiene; Education, Rural; Child welfare; Child psychology; Child mental health; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Public health; Public welfare
- Administrative Files, 1944-1984; 1; 8 box(es)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges (John A.D. Cooper et. al., AAMC/CF Meeting, February 7, 1975), February 5-24, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bok, Derek ( "Needed: A New Way to Train Doctors" - Article and Criticism of Same), May-November, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Boston University (Silber, John R.), 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boston University (Silber, John R.), 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Boston University (Silber, John R.), 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Boston University (Site Visit March 3-4, 1976), January-March, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Boston University (Site Visit March 15-16, 1979), March 5-17, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Boston University (Site Visit November 21, 1974), 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brown University (Site Visit March 15-16, 1977), February-March, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - University of California-San Diego (Interface Conference April 3-5, 1982), April 3-12, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - University of California-San Diego (Proposal and Site Visit), 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - University of California-San Francisco (Site Visit December 14, 1973), 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chapman, Carleton B. (The Future of Commonwealth Fund Programs - Memoranda), 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - University of Chicago (Application for Support of the ASHUM Program), 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - University of Chicago (Correspondence - Chapman to Jacobsen and Levy), 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - University of Chicago (Proposal and Memoranda), January-March, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - University of Chicago (Site Visit December 19, 1973), 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - University of Chicago (Site Visit February 19-20, 1976), January-March, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Columbia University (Site Visit December 11, 1973), 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Conference I on Interface (May 25, 1977), April-June, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Conference II on Interface (February 17, 1978), 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Conference II on Interface (February 17, 1978) - Supplementary Material (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Conference III on Interface (June 1, 1978), March-June, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Conference IV on Interface (October 19, 1978) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Conference V on Interface (April 18, 1979), February-April, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Cooperative Programs of Brown University/Dartmouth College, February-October, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Council on Foundations, Inc. (Annual Conference April 22-25, 1975), March-April, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Dartmouth College (Kemey, John), 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Dartmouth College (Proposal), August 12, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Donway, Walter, October 24, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Duke University (Correspondence), 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Duke University (Proposal Draft #1), July 20, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Duke University (Proposal Draft #2), August 27, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Duke University (Site Visit November 19, 1973) (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Duke University (Site Visit September 20-22, 1976), September-October, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Duke University (Site Visit November 26-28, 1979), October-November, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Equitable Life Insurance Co., May-November, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Evaluation and Final Recommendations of the Interface Program, February 2, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Federation of Public Programs in the Humanities (Reports), April-June, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Future Commonwealth Fund Programs/Interface Statements, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Gellhorn, Alfred (Correspondence), 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Gellhorn, Alfred (Report), April 1980 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - General Correspondence, 1975-1982 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Group Process Model for Problem Identification and Program Planning, July 12, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Hahnemann Medical College and Hospital (Site Visit February 13, 1976), February-March, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Harvard Medical School (Ebert, Robert H.), 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Hastings Institute, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - HEW, February-June, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Hunterdon Medical Center (Site Visit January 14, 1977), January 14-18, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - The Imagination Workshop, February 6, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Inquiries Regarding Interface, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - International Council on the Future of the University, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Johns Hopkins University (General File), 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Johns Hopkins University (Muller and Ross Correspondence), 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Johns Hopkins University (Proposal), June 1977 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Johns Hopkins University (Site Visit), July-October, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Kass, Leon R. ("Regarding the End of Medicine and the Pursuit of Health"), 1975 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Letters to College Presidents (Commonwealth Fund Interface Proposal), 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Massachusetts General Hospital, January-March, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - McMaster University (Simpson, Michael A.), 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - McMaster University (Site Visit April 21-22, 1975), March-June, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - McMaster University (Supplementary Material), 1972 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Meeting I on Interface (May 14, 1973), April-May, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Meeting II on Interface (August 21, 1973), April-September, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Meeting III on Interface (March 7, 1974), 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Meeting IV on Interface (January 13, 1975), 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Meeting V on Interface (June 4, 1975), April-June, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Meeting VI on Interface (October 12-13, 1980), September-October, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - University of Michigan, March 1, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Miller, Alfred, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Memoranda, 1975-1982 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Miscellaneous Reprints, 1944-1982 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - MIT (Site Visit December 19, 1975), December 19-22, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - MIT (Wiesner, Jerome B.), 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Mount Sinai School of Medicine (Site Visit), October 22, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Mount Zion Hospital (Site Visit November 12, 1976), November-December, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - National Health Council, June 1977 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Natural Sciences Medical School of Arts and Sciences (University of Pennsylvania), March 31, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - New Jersey College of Medicine, May-June, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - New York Academy of Medicine, March 26, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - New York Medical College (Proposal), May 6, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - New York University Medical Center Urban Health Affairs Program (Site Visit), February 24-25, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Ohio State University, April 2, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - University of Oregon (Summer Lectures), July-August, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - University of Pennsylvania, 1974-1977 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Peter Bent Brigham Hospital (Braunwald, Eugene), 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Press Release (November 18, 1975) and Commentary on the Interface Program, November-December, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Princeton University, July-August, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Private Foundations and Medical Education (Correspondence), 1973-1976 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Private Foundations and Medical Education (Correspondence), 1973-1976 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Private Foundations and Medical Education (Correspondence), 1973-1976 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - University of Rochester (Rochester Plan Proposals), 1975-1977 (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - University of Rochester (Site Visit September 27-28, 1977), June-October, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Stanford University (Lyman, Richard W.), 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Statement on Interface Program (June 1976), April-June, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Summary of Interface Program, 1977-1981 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Travel Expenses (Mack Lipkin), 1975-1979 (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Tufts University (Proposal and Site Visit), 1976-1978 (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - Vanderbilt University (Heard, Alexander), 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - University of Vermont, February-November, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - Visits Regarding Final Proposal Under the Interface Program, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - Warren, James V., 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - Washington University, St. Louis (Site Visit), undated (Box 8, Folder 103)
  - "What to Ask of a College" (Edwin P. Taylor), September 9-17, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - Yale University (Brewster and Berliner Correspondence), 1974-1976 (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - Yale University (Silver, George Correspondence), 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - Zacharias, Jerrold, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - Zacharias, Leona, April 6-20, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - Zugar, Abby ("The Birth of a Doctor"), August 29, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 109)
- Grant Files, 1974-1984; 2; 10 box(es)
  - Boston University, 1974-1981 (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - Boston University, 1974-1981 (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Boston University, 1974-1981 (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Boston University, 1974-1981 (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Boston University, 1974-1981 (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - Boston University, 1974-1981 (Box 9, Folder 115)
  - Boston University (Final Evaluation Report), September 1980 (Box 9, Folder 116)
  - Boston University (Proposal), September 30, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 117)
  - Boston University (Proposal), September 30, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - Boston University (Proposal), February 27, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - Boston University (Proposal), March 1, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - Boston University (Supplementary Material), 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - Boston University (Supplementary Material), 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - Brown University, 1976-1981 (Box 10, Folder 123)
  - Brown University, 1976-1981 (Box 10, Folder 124)
  - Brown University, 1976-1981 (Box 10, Folder 125)
  - Brown University (Supplementary Material), 1976-1980 (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - Brown University (Supplementary Material), 1976-1980 (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - University of Chicago, 1974-1979 (Box 11, Folder 128)
  - University of Chicago, 1974-1979 (Box 11, Folder 129)
  - University of Chicago, 1974-1979 (Box 11, Folder 130)
  - University of Chicago (Progress Report), July 1978 (Box 11, Folder 131)
  - University of Chicago (Proposal), December 15, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 132)
  - University of Chicago (Site Visit), February 18-20, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 133)
  - University of Chicago - Renewed Support - Experimental Program, Arts and Sciences - Basics of Human Biology and Medicine (Box 11A)
  - University of Chicago (Site Visit), January 10-12, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 134)
  - Dartmouth College and Medical School, 1975-1980 (Box 12, Folder 135)
  - Dartmouth College and Medical School, 1975-1980 (Box 12, Folder 136)
  - Dartmouth College and Medical School, 1975-1980 (Box 12, Folder 137)
  - Dartmouth College and Medical School (Proposal), August 1976 (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - Dartmouth College and Medical School (Site Visit), January 6-7, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - Duke University, 1976-1980 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - Duke University, 1976-1980 (Box 12, Folder 141)
  - Duke University, 1976-1980 (Box 12, Folder 142)
  - Duke University (Evaluation Report), 1979 (Box 13, Folder 143)
  - Duke University (Proposal #1 and #2), July-August, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 144)
  - Duke University (Renewal Grant), 1979-1984 (Box 13, Folder 145)
  - Duke University (Renewal Grant), 1979-1984 (Box 13, Folder 146)
  - Duke University (Renewal Grant), 1979-1984 (Box 13, Folder 147)
  - Duke University (Renewal Grant - Evaluation Report), 1980 (Box 13, Folder 148)
  - Duke University (Renewal Grant - Final Report Appendices), August 1983 (Box 13, Folder 149)
  - Duke University (Renewal Grant - Proposal), October 1979 (Box 13, Folder 150)
  - Duke University (Renewal Grant - Proposal), October 1979 (Box 14, Folder 151)
  - Duke University (Site Visit), September 20-22, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 152)
  - Duke University (Supplementary Material), September 26, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 153)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1974-1984 (Box 14, Folder 154)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1974-1984 (Box 14, Folder 155)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1974-1984 (Box 14, Folder 156)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1974-1984 (Box 14, Folder 157)
  - Johns Hopkins University, 1974-1984 (Box 14, Folder 158)
  - Johns Hopkins University (Supplementary Material), 1977 and 1980 (Box 15, Folder 159)
  - Johns Hopkins University (Supplementary Material), 1977 and 1980 (Box 15, Folder 160)
  - University of Rochester, 1974-1977 (Box 15, Folder 161)
  - University of Rochester, 1974-1977 (Box 15, Folder 162)
  - University of Rochester, 1974-1977 (Box 15, Folder 163)
  - University of Rochester, 1974-1977 (Box 15, Folder 164)
  - University of Rochester, 1974-1977 (Box 15, Folder 165)
  - University of Rochester, 1977-1984 (Box 16, Folder 166)
  - University of Rochester, 1977-1984 (Box 16, Folder 167)
  - University of Rochester, 1977-1984 (Box 16, Folder 168)
  - University of Rochester, 1977-1984 (Box 16, Folder 169)
  - University of Rochester (Inquiries and Comments), 1975-1976 (Box 16, Folder 170)
  - University of Rochester (Supplementary Material), 1975-1977 (Box 16, Folder 171)
  - University of Rochester (Supplementary Material), 1975-1977 (Box 16, Folder 172)
  - University of Rochester (Supplementary Material), 1977-1980 (Box 17, Folder 173)
  - University of Rochester (Supplementary Material), 1977-1980 (Box 17, Folder 174)
  - University of Rochester (Supplementary Material), 1977-1980 (Box 17, Folder 175)